ARGHYA CHATTERJEE



arghyame20buet@gmail.com

https://arghyachatterjee.github.io

A machine learning researcher experienced in applying Deep Learning, Edge & Cloud Computing for Computer Vision (CV) related applications, Advanced Perception (CV & LIDAR) based SLAM for semantic awareness of the environment, Multi-agent collaboration for autonomous robotic exploration in perceptually degraded environments and Swarm Intelligence for rapid & effective exploration of outer space to help make better decision for humans.

EDUCATION

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Degree: BSc. in Mechanical Engineering Feb 2015 - Sept 2019

CGPA: 3.14/4.00

Khulna Public College, Khulna, Bangladesh

Degree: HSC in Science Jul 2012 - Aug 2014 GPA: 5.00/5.00 Class Position: $1^{st}/60$

• Khulna Bidyut Kendra Secondary School, Khulna, Bangladesh

Degree: SSC in Science Jan 2010 - May 2012

GPA: 5.00/5.00 Class Position: 1st/60

RESEARCH & PROJECT EXPERIENCE

Team Member, Team CoSTAR of NASA JPL

DARPA organized SubT Challenge Perception Team Leader: Dr. Benjamin Morrell (NASA JPL) Jul 2020 – Present *California, USA*

Topic: Advanced perception based multi-robot SLAM algorithms efficiency, accuracy & robustness testing along with object detection & localization capability analysis for robots like Spot, Husky & Roller-copter with special autonomy setup (built by Team CoSTAR) mounted.

Team Supervisor & Educator, STEMX 365

JAXA (& NASA) org. Kibo-Astrobee ISS Robot Programming Challenge Jan 2020 – Present International Project Coordinator: Mizanul H. Chowdhury (MIT) Tokyo, Japan Topic: Autonomously operate Astrobee (A free flying robot) inside ISS avoiding obstacles with 3D perception, following way points and detecting QR & AR Tag.

Graduate Research Assistant at Mars Rover Lab, BUET

Software Team Advisor (& Ex. Lead) of Interplanetar for URC & ERC

Sep 2019 – Present

Supervisor: Dr. Md. Ashiqur Rahman (BUET)

Topic: Autonomous Navigation Based on GPS, SLAM, AR Tag and Object Detection for Safe

Exploration of Rovers on Rough Terrains, Caves and Mineral Ores of Earth and Mars.

Researcher & Collaborator, BUET

Undergraduate Thesis

Supervisors: Dr. Maglub Al Nur (BUET) and Dr. Muhammad Abir (MIT)

Dhaka, Bangladesh
Topic: Computational Investigation on Pool Boiling IR Images for Segmentation of Dry Spots
Automatically and Evaluating Performance of Traditional Image Processing and Deep Neural
Networks in Quantifying Dry Area Segments.

• Researcher & Team Leader, BUET

Undergraduate Project

Supervisors: Dr. M.A. Rashid Sarkar and Musanna Galib (BUET)

Topic: Fire and Flood Fighter Octocopter (UAV) for Extinguishing Fire in Fire Affected Buildings and Areas, and Distributing Flood Reliefs to people in Flood Affected Zones.

• Researcher & Technical Leader, Team Out of the Box

Microsoft BD Internship Project

Jan 2017 - Mar 2017

Supervisors: Sonia B. Kabir and Ashikur Rahman (Microsoft)

Topic: Earlier Screening of Particular Disability in Children Through Mobile Application Using Microsoft Products like Azure Cloud Platform and Bing Maps Server.

• Researcher & Team Leader, BUET

Undergraduate Project

Supervisors: Dr. M.A. Rashid Sarkar and Dr. A. B. M. Alim Al Islam (BUET)

Dhaka, Bangladesh
Topic: Hand Wearable Solar Powered Obstacle Detection and Safe Navigation Device for Blind
People in Low Cost.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

•	STEMX 365 for JAXA Kibo Astrobee ISS RPC	Jan 2020 - Present
	Educator & Instructor of Teams from Bangladesh	Dhaka, Bangladesh
•	BUET Mars Rover Robotics Team	Sep 2019 - Present
	Instructor at Model & Project Lab (Mars Rover Lab), BUET	Dhaka, Bangladesh
•	National Space Carnival & Camp	Sep 2019 - Jun 2020
	Instructor & Academic Coordinator for Workshops & Camps	Dhaka, Bangladesh
•	Bangladesh Astronomical Society	Mar 2017 – Apr 2019
	Instructor for Workshops & Seminars	Dhaka, Bangladesh

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

•	Bangladesh Astronomy Research Collaboration (BARC)	Jan 2020 – Present
	Advisor & Fellow Member	Dhaka, Bangladesh
	Activities: Give advice on research activities & how the organization should operate.	

● Youthprenuer Network (A Social Welfare Organization)

Head of STEM Education & Development

Activities: Instructed, Organized and Lead Projects, Workshops, Olympiads and Camps in Educational Institutions to Promote STEM Education in Bangladesh.

American Astronomical Society

Country Collaborator & Member

Activities: Celebrated International Astronomical Events in Bangladesh and Reported to Proper AAS Authority for Publishing on their Magazines.

PUBLICATIONS

- Matteo Palieri, Benjamin Morrell, Abhishek Thakur, Kamak Ebadi, Jeremy Nash, Arghya Chatterjee, Christoforos Kanellakis, Luca Carlone, Cataldo Guaragnella, Ali-akbar Aghamohammadi, "LOCUS: A Multi-Sensor Lidar-Centric Solution for High-Precision Odometry and 3D Mapping in Real-Time," IEEE Robotics & Automation Letters Journal, 2020, vol: 6/2, pp. 421-428.
- Arghya Chatterjee, M. Galib and M. A. R. Sarkar, "Application of Arduino in designing modern electromechanical laboratory," 2017 IEEE International Conference on Power, Control, Signals and Instrumentation Engineering (ICPCSI), Chennai, 2017, pp. 222-225.
- Arghya Chatterjee, S. Dutta, P. Sarkar and A. B. M. A. A. Islam, "Obstacle Detector for Blind People with Low Cost (Poster Presentation)," *Proceedings of* 2017 International Conference on Networking, Systems and Security (NSysS), Dhaka, 2017.

INTERNSHIPS & TRAININGS

•	Microsoft Bangladesh Limited	Jan 2017 - Mar 2017
	Internship Project: Disabling Disability through Microsoft Products	Dhaka, Bangladesh
•	Khulna Power Company Limited	Oct 2018 - Oct 2018
	Training: Power Plant Visit & Industrial Attachment (3 weeks)	Khulna, Bangladesh

SKILL SETS

- Prg. Language: Python, C++, C#, C, R, Arduino, Java, Java S, HTML, PHP, CSS, & LATEX.
- Framework & OS: ROS, OpenCV, PCL, Nvidia Isaac SDK, Keras, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Caffe, CUDA, OpenGL, Kubernetes, .NET, Django, Linux, Mac, Windows & Android.
- Software & Tool: Git & GitHub, Docker, MIPAR, Solidworks, Ansys, PLC, Blender, Unity & UE 4, Verge3D, Carla Simulator, Microsoft Airsim, OpenPose3D, Meshroom, Meshlab, CloudCompare, OpenDroneMap, OpenSpace, Photoshop, Kdenlive & MS Office Family.
- IDE, Compiler & Text Editor: CodeBlocks, Microsoft Visual Studio, MATLAB, Atom, Jupiter Notebook, PyCharm, Android Studio, Nodejs, IntelliJ IDEA, VS Code & Notepad++.
- Cloud Platform: AWS Compute, AWS RoboMaker & Storage, GCP, Google Colab.
- Hardware: GPS (RTK), IMU, VLP-16 (3D) & RPLidar (2D) LIDAR, Intel Realsense D435i RGBD & L515 Lidar Camera, ZED 3D Camera, Nvidia Jetson & Intel NUC Boards, Arduino & Raspberry PI Boards, PX4, Ardupilot, VESC, BLDC motor, Nvidia AMD GTX Boards & Oculus Rift S VR Headset.
- Technology: Computer Vision, Image Proc., ML, DL, DRL, Object Detection & Recognition, Image Segmentation, Pose Tracking, SLAM, Photogrammetry, 3D Printing, AR, VR & MR, Game Dev, Web Dev, Video Editing, GPU, Edge & Cloud Computing.
- Language: Bangla, English & Hindi.
- Others: Astronomy, Creative Arts, Singing, Harmonium & Guitar Playing, Organizing, Show Hosting, Volunteering, Swimming, Cycling, Playing Cricket, Football & Badminton.

AWARDS, HONORS & SCHOLARSHIPS

Gold Medalist from Duke of Edinburgh International Foundation	Dec 2019
Awarded for Outstanding Extra-curricular & Service to the Society	London, UK
• 2 nd in Asia & 16 th Internationally in European Mars Rover Challenge	Sep 2019
European Space Foundation (ESF) & European Space Agency (ESA)	Kielce, PL
• Finalist in IEEE SS12 International Project Competition & Maker Fair	Jul 2017
SS12: Age of Innovation and Maker Fair 2017	Hyderabad, IN
• 1 st in National Project Show Competition (Senior Category)	May 2017
EEE Day, BUET	Dhaka, BD
 3rd in Inter University Project Show Competition 	Apr 2017
Mechanical Festival, BUET	Dhaka, BD
• 1 st in National Poster Presentation Competition	Mar 2017
Robolution, MIST	Dhaka, BD
 2nd in Inter University Project Show Competition 	Nov 2016
CSE Day, BUET	Dhaka, BD
• 1st in All Classes in Primary, Junior, Secondary & H. Secondary	2002-2014
Elizabeth Primary Sc., Khulna BKS Sc., Khulna Pub. Cl.	Khulna, BD
Govt. Board Scholarship in Primary, Junior, Secondary & H. Secondary	2006-2014
Education Board of Bangladesh Govt., Jessore	Khulna, BD
Olympiad Achievements:	
• 1 st in Reg. R. of Science Olympiad'14 • 1 st in Reg. R. of Zo	ology Olympiad'14

• 3rd in Reg. R. of Math Olympiad'14

CERTIFICATIONS

• Machine Learning by Stanford University on Coursera, Feb 2018.

• 3rd in Reg. & 10th in Nat. R. of Astro-Olympiad'13

- **Deep Learning Specialization** (5 course) by Deeplearning.ai on Coursera, Sept 2018.
- **Control of Mobile Robots** by Georgia Institute of Technology on Coursera. May 2020.
- Image & Video Processing by Duke University on Coursera, Nov 2018.
- Intro to Satellite Communications by Institut Mines Télécom on Coursera, May 2019.

- Wireless Communications for Everybody by Yonsei University on Coursera, Dec 2018.
- **AstroTech** by University of Edinburgh on Coursera, Dec 2019.
- A Course on Nuclear Power Eng. by Institute of Nuclear Power Engineering, BUET, Apr 2018.

LEADERSHIPS

• **Head** of STEM Education & Development

Software Team Lead

• **Technical Lead** of Internship Project

• **President** (Senior Rover Mate)

President

• Team Lead for Development & Planning

Youthprenuer Network
Team Interplanetar, BUET
Microsoft BD
BUET Rover Scout Group
Satyen Bose Science Club, BUET
ESAB. BUET Unit

VOLUNTEERING

Sceptre (Poverty Alleviation Organization)

Activities: Org. free medical camps & distribute dress & sewing machines to poor people.

BUET Rover Scout Group

Activities: Volunteered on alumni day at BUET & org. flood relief distribution camp.

• Khulna Bidyut Kendra Secondary School Scout Group
Activities: Volunteered on medical camps, tree plantation events & sports day at KBKSS.

SEMINARS & WORKSHOPS

- International Youth Leadership Summit-2016 org. by BYLC.
- 4th BIRDS International Workshop on **Demystifying Satellites** org. by BRAC University.
- Seminar on **Zero Robotics** by M.H. Chowdhury of MIT org. by Dept. of Mech. Eng., BUET.
- Seminar on **Space Stories and ISS Experiences** by Astronaut Dr. Tess Caswell of NASA org. by Dept. of Civil Eng., BUET.
- Seminar on **4-fold Resolution Increase in Endoscopic Imaging** by J.M. Kahn of Stanford University, org. by Dept. of Biomedical Eng., BUET.
- Workshop on **ML, PCB, Graphic Designing, & Technical Paper Writing** org. by IEEE BDS.
- Workshop on CFD, Ansys Fluent, Solidworks & 3D Printing org. by Involute Tech BD.

MEMBERSHIPS

- Institute of Electrical and Electronics Eng. (IEEE)
- American Nuclear Society (ANS)
- Bangladesh Astronomy Research Collaboration
- American Astronomical Society (AAS)
- IEEE Robotics and Automation Society
- BYLC Graduate Network (BGN)

REFERENCES

Dr. Benjamin Morrell

Perception Team Leader, Team CoSTAR Ex. Post Doc. Researcher, JPL, Caltech. Robotics Technologist, NASA JPL. Email: benjamin.morrell@jpl.nasa.gov

Dr. Md. Ashigur Rahman

Project Supervisor Professor, Dept. of Mech. Eng., BUET. Email: ashiqurrahman@me.buet.ac.bd Dr. Muhammad Abir

Thesis Co-Supervisor Ex. Post Doc. Researcher, Dept. of NSE, MIT. Imaging Specialist, Phoenix Nuclear Labs. Email: miabir@mit.edu

• Mizanul H. Chowdhury

Project Supervisor Arch. & Admin of ZR, Space Systems Lab, MIT. Email: mizanul@mit.edu